<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the kingdom stated according to the proper interests of the severall parties ingaged : I. Touching the interest of the King and his party, II. The interest of the Presbyterian party, III. The interest of the Independent party, IV. The interest of the citie of London, V. The interest of Scotland, not extant before now : a peece of rare observation and contexture, wherin all men are equally concerned.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40043</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18670086</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18670086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1658:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the kingdom stated according to the proper interests of the severall parties ingaged : I. Touching the interest of the King and his party, II. The interest of the Presbyterian party, III. The interest of the Independent party, IV. The interest of the citie of London, V. The interest of Scotland, not extant before now : a peece of rare observation and contexture, wherin all men are equally concerned.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 [i.e. 14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 7-8 omitted in numbering only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108136:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108136:1"/>
            <p>The Caſe of the KINGDOM STATED, According to the Proper Intereſts of the ſeverall Parties INGAGED.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Touching the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>KING</hi> and his <hi>Party.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Party.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Independent Party.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the Citie of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> not extant before now.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A peece of rare Obſervation and Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; wherin all men are equally Concerned.</p>
            <p>The Third <hi>Edition,</hi> with Addition by the Author <hi>M. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Dulce, &amp; decorum eſt pro Patriâ.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <div type="author_to_king">
               <pb facs="tcp:108136:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To the KING.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter ſo many <hi>ſtorms</hi> I know you would willingly attain the wiſhed <hi>Haven,</hi> but then you muſt <hi>imbarque</hi> a new, and not in the old <hi>Shipwrack't de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</hi> And ſince it is no <hi>Flattery</hi> to wiſh you well, for your own ſake, and many others, pray take this <hi>Pamphlet to ſteer</hi> your courſe by, and account him as good a friend to your ſelf and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as any you have bin acquainted with theſe ſeven yeers, who firſt delivers it into your hands: For, I am confident, were you abroad among your old <hi>Councell,</hi> you ſhould not reap ſo much of the truth of your <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as you may in theſe poor <hi>ſheets,</hi> which are but the <hi>Gleanings</hi> of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_presbyters">
               <head>To the PRESBYTERS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sweet SIRS:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Let not your <hi>Jealouſie</hi> accuſe this <hi>Paper</hi> of a <hi>Plot</hi> againſt the <hi>State:</hi> Truly I have added your <hi>Intereſt</hi> out of pitty to your condition, that ſince you cannot attain your <hi>Jure divino,</hi> you may (at leaſt) open your eyes, and preſerve your ſelves (if you pleaſe) in a handſome equipage, <hi>Jure humano.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_independents">
               <head>To the INDEPENDENTS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>FRIENDS:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>You who are Liſted more immediatly under the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> ought not ſo to proſecute your <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as to begin a <hi>War</hi> upon it; but only to remain on the <hi>defenſive</hi> till your juſt <hi>Liberty</hi> be confirmed, and the <hi>Prince</hi>'s due right reſtored, ſince <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt needs remain quieter, where the power is inveſted in one <hi>King,</hi> than in an <hi>Hydra</hi> of Presbyters. Above all things you muſt not be <hi>Anti-parliamentary,</hi> but exerciſe wiſdome with patience, and the countenance of that <hi>Authority</hi> cannot long be wanting: <hi>A word to the wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_london">
               <head>To the CITY.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIRS:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>My deſire is, that you may flouriſh, which cannot be, unleſſe you minde only your peculiar <hi>Intereſt</hi> of Trade. If you reſolve to live and die with Presbytery, conſider that you can ill <hi>Bandy</hi> againſt the other two <hi>Parties,</hi> ſince it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, that they are the <hi>major</hi> part of your ſelves. <hi>A City divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_scots">
               <head>To the SCOTS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friends and Confederates:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Take this brief draught of your <hi>Intereſt,</hi> wherewith I here preſent you, with the ſame <hi>Ingenuity</hi> and <hi>Candor,</hi> that I wrote it. <hi>God</hi> ſhall bear me record, that I lay nothing open here, with <hi>intent</hi> to work <hi>diviſion,</hi> it being contrary to my <hi>obligation</hi> by <hi>Covenant;</hi> but onely to ſatisfie the <hi>world</hi> in <hi>truth</hi> concerning <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>your ſelves</hi> in what concerns your own <hi>happineſſe, ſafety,</hi> and <hi>advantage,</hi> by a wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, in order to the Conſervaton of Peace in theſe Kingdoms. <hi>Honi ſoit qui mal y penſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_all_above">
               <p>And now (Gentlemen) but one word more to all: I ſuppoſe none can take juſt offence, ſince I ſtate the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of all indifferently, pointing out to each the way to advance and preſerve their own <hi>Party,</hi> and I ſhall commend to them what the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> ſaith of the States of <hi>Europe,</hi> that according as they follow their proper <hi>Intereſts,</hi> they thrive or faile in <hi>Succeſſes,</hi> ſo the <hi>Parties</hi> now on Foot in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> muſt looke to ſtand or fall upon the ſame Ground.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108136:2"/>
            <head>The Caſe of the Kingdom ſtated, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Firſt, touching the Intereſt of the</hi> KING <hi>and his Partie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>King</hi> (as the caſe lately ſtood with <hi>him</hi>) was a very <hi>Priſoner;</hi> and ſo being fallen from the height of <hi>fortune,</hi> muſt remit much of the height of his <hi>deſigne;</hi> and what hath been loſt by <hi>bandy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> he ought to <hi>Salve</hi> by a wary <hi>Compliance.</hi> That <hi>this</hi> he may effect in a ſhort time is very probable, ſince what <hi>Machiavell</hi> ſets downe as a ſure <hi>Principle</hi> towards the purchaſe of <hi>Empire</hi> is acted ready to his <hi>hands,</hi> by the mutuall expence of <hi>Spleene</hi> in his <hi>oppoſites</hi> againſt each other: ſo that all he hath to doe is to ſit <hi>ſtill,</hi> to <hi>foment</hi> and <hi>blow</hi> the Fire, and give the <hi>humours</hi> time to <hi>toyle,</hi> till being tyred in <hi>extreames</hi> there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of one <hi>Third</hi> to reſt in, (which can be no other but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;) and then his onely <hi>Intereſt</hi> will be, to <hi>cloſe</hi> with that <hi>Party</hi> which gives moſt <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>Indulgence</hi> to his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> &amp; greateſt probability of <hi>favor</hi> to his <hi>Friends.</hi> That neither of theſe can be expected from the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyterian,</hi> is evident for many <hi>Reaſons:</hi> And firſt touching the <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> their <hi>Government</hi> in the nature of it <hi>derogates</hi> not onely from the <hi>Civill</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> but carries with it a more ſpeciall enmity againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie;</hi> ſo that they which intend to <hi>found</hi> the one, muſt <hi>raze</hi> the <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals</hi> of the other in any <hi>Kingdome</hi> whatſoever. <hi>Politique</hi> aſſertions of this kinde ſhould be ſtrengthned by Obſervations out of Hiſtory: But the <hi>tender</hi> age of this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pstart Hierarchy</hi> and the <hi>Little</hi> entertainment it hath found in the <hi>World,</hi> yeelds us nothing of moment to obſerve, unleſſe in our own <hi>Iſland.</hi> For if we looke abroad, we finde it but ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling up and downe in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and in ſuch <hi>places</hi> onely as acknowledge <hi>little</hi> or <hi>none</hi> at all of <hi>Kingly</hi> power; ſo that <hi>Scotland</hi> is the onely <hi>viſible</hi> Kingome where this <hi>Peſt</hi> is <hi>Epidemicall,</hi> and it was (firſt) <hi>Scotch</hi> Charity to <hi>Baptize</hi> it as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> into the name and priviledge of a <hi>Nationall Forme.</hi> This was done during the minority of King <hi>James,</hi> when the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Clergie</hi> ruling all as they <hi>liſted,</hi> at length <hi>parted ſtakes</hi> (though the <hi>Clergie</hi> then got, and ſtill hold the better) that when He came to age, he found the Fable of <hi>Ixion's Juno</hi> moralized upon himſelf; for as he inſtead of a <hi>Goddeſſe</hi> imbraced a <hi>Cloud;</hi> ſo the <hi>King,</hi> when he thought to graſp his <hi>Scepter,</hi> laid hold on a <hi>Manacle,</hi> which kept his hands ſo faſt, during his abode there, that he could never Act but when they pleaſed to let him, according to their own <hi>Directory</hi> of <hi>Kirk</hi> and State: And in proceſſe of time this heat of <hi>Presbytery</hi> proved ſuch an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108136:3"/>
                  <hi>Hectique</hi> in the body <hi>Politique</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the Subſtance of <hi>Kingly power</hi> was utterly conſumed, and nothing left (as we ſee at this day) but the bare bones, the very <hi>Ek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leton</hi> of a <hi>Monarchie;</hi> Witneſſe the unlimited power of the <hi>Convention of Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>Generall Aſſembly,</hi> but eſpecially of this latter, which (like to the Rod of <hi>Aaron</hi>) is in ſuch a budding, thriving condition, that it hath devoured the Rod of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as his did the Magicians of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and proves a Scourge to the <hi>Magiſtracie</hi> and <hi>People.</hi> This is a ſufficient <hi>Inſtance</hi> (being alſo the onely one in the World) to manifeſt the <hi>Antipathie</hi> betwixt a <hi>Nationall Presbytery,</hi> and the <hi>civill</hi> power of <hi>Common weales</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> wherein whoſoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires further ſatisfaction, needs doe no more but take a ſtrict ſurvey of their owne Bookes of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, touching the <hi>Kings Friends</hi> [which are of two Sorts, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Clergie,</hi> the <hi>Courtiers</hi> with the <hi>Gentry,</hi>] they muſt expect leſſe from the <hi>Presbyter</hi> than the King himſelfe may: For, as They would leave the <hi>King</hi> nothing but a <hi>name</hi> without <hi>Substance,</hi> ſo they will allow the <hi>Biſhops</hi> neither Name nor <hi>Substance,</hi> and inſlave the <hi>Gentry</hi> in their own <hi>Lordſhips</hi> by a new way of <hi>par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chiall Tyrannie:</hi> For, if ſo be they <hi>conforme</hi> not, then they muſt expect in a ſhort time to ſee the meaneſt of their <hi>Tenants</hi> become their <hi>Maſters</hi> in judicature, and ſo what <hi>Solomon</hi> cals a great <hi>Vanitie,</hi> will be a <hi>Prime myſtery</hi> in this new <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence, then we may conclude, that the Kings <hi>Intereſts</hi> lead him to cloſe rather with the other party (called <hi>Independent</hi>) as the onely means to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>friends,</hi> from the former <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> and that for theſe following <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe they are the onely friends to <hi>Civil</hi> government in the <hi>World,</hi> leaving it wholly in the hands of the <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> pleading <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption</hi> in nothing but their <hi>Church-way:</hi> Whereas the <hi>Presbyters</hi> claim not onely a diſtinct power in <hi>Church-affaires</hi> [as you may read in that <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Synods</hi> late <hi>confeſſion</hi> which ſpeakes of <hi>Church cenſures</hi>] but they borrow alſo ſo much from the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> as will in able them to <hi>compell</hi> mens Conſciences: And ſo under this cunning <hi>Pretence,</hi> that the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> is bound to uſe or lend his power to ſupport their <hi>arbitrary conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> [the Proofes whereof they Fiſh out of the <hi>Judicials</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſome places of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> miſapplyed in ſome of their <hi>Articles</hi>] lurkes the great <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> whereby They gaine a power even over the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> himſelfe, who in this caſe muſt uſe the <hi>ſword</hi> (for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake) whereſoever they pleaſe to <hi>Adviſe</hi> or <hi>Command</hi> him: And ſo both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt give way, and <hi>compell</hi> others to ſubmit, to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108136:3"/>
whatſoever they ſhall ordain in their <hi>Generall Aſſembly,</hi> as <hi>for the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governing of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly; becauſe it is eaſie for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>King</hi> to mingle <hi>Intereſts</hi> with the <hi>Independents,</hi> and oblige them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> that which is denyed them by the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> viz. <hi>Liberty of conſcience:</hi> In which Particular he ought alſo to pretend great tenderneſſe, it being his <hi>owne</hi> caſe at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſuffer by many preſſing <hi>Importunities,</hi> to take the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and paſſe things of high Importance wherein he is not ſatisfied, the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall whereof upon <hi>Scruple</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is the only cauſe of his <hi>non-acceſſe</hi> to the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe the <hi>Independent</hi> Principles lead them to admit rather of <hi>Monarchy</hi> than any other <hi>Government,</hi> as being that under which they preſume of greater <hi>Inlargements,</hi> than when <hi>Many</hi> rule; who are uſually moſt apt to gratifie a faction in the <hi>Nationall Church</hi> with accruments of worldly pomp and power, the better to ſupport their own in the <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Here is a doore of Hope opened this way for the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Clergie,</hi> with all that are for the <hi>Liturgie</hi> and that Government, Whereas, if <hi>Presbytrie</hi> take place in a <hi>Nationall mode,</hi> then there will be <hi>Form</hi> againſt their <hi>Form,</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> againſt their <hi>Policie,</hi> which when it ſhall be actually twiſted with that of the <hi>State,</hi> can never be removed without length of time and extreme difficulty. Where obſerve by the way, how it was ever the <hi>grand</hi> myſtery which <hi>Satan</hi> ſet on work in the hearts of thoſe who glory in that uſurped <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Clergie;</hi> firſt to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a <hi>plauſible, politique, prudentiall</hi> way of Government in the <hi>Church,</hi> as the only <hi>pattern brought out of the Mount;</hi> then to gain it a ſure being and repute with men, thy were wont to take in ſome of the power of the <hi>World</hi> to countenance it, and force a Submiſſion thereto by all, under the <hi>old ſpecious</hi> pretext of <hi>Decency, Conformity,</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> and laſtly to make all faſt, the Cuſtome was to mingle <hi>Intereſts</hi> with the <hi>State</hi> or the <hi>Prince</hi> [as the <hi>Biſhops</hi> lately did with our <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters</hi> doe now with ſome <hi>great Ones</hi> and the <hi>City</hi>] and ſo their <hi>Fundamentalls</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once poys'd with the others, then whoſoever ſhall preſume to move the one, muſt ſhake the other, and preſently incurre the <hi>brand</hi> of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious diſturbers of <hi>States</hi> and Kingdomes; Which hath been no meane artifice of the <hi>Devill</hi> [in all times] to uphold his Kingdom in the hearts of men, againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> In this Particular the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> have been alike faulty; But if theſe have time to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant the <hi>Biſhops</hi> [as they are in a fair way] and over-act them at their owne <hi>game,</hi> They are left for ever without remedy. But</p>
               <p>Fifthly, by an immediate <hi>Cloſe</hi> with the <hi>Independent,</hi> and abandoning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108136:4"/>
that curſed Principle of <hi>univerſall Compulſion,</hi> as well in opinion as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, ſince there is a numerous ſort of people in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that will not be ſatisfied, without the old <hi>external</hi> Form of <hi>Dioceſan &amp; Liturgie;</hi> it's clear then, that <hi>Independents</hi> may help to Inſtate Them in that <hi>Forme</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, upon ſome viſible aſſurance, that themſelves ſhall be left at <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> rather then be trodden down, by a <hi>Mornivall</hi> [or two] of <hi>Tyrants</hi> [no leſſe monſtrous [perhaps] for <hi>Ignorance,</hi> than pride] in every <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall Inquiſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt Reaſon is, becauſe the Kings <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with this party may ſo abate the fury of the <hi>Presbiter,</hi> that (whether <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>War</hi> enſue) thoſe of the <hi>Court, Councell, and Gentry</hi> excepted from pardon, and the reſt that have not yet <hi>Compounded,</hi> cannot continue long at this diſtance, without ſome, <hi>probable</hi> hope, That Humors altering, and by the mediation of ſome the reſt being brought to a more <hi>moderate temper,</hi> it may be no hard matter to reconcile <hi>all</hi> within the Limits of an <hi>Act of Oblivion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo for theſe</hi> Reaſons <hi>I conceive, we may boldly affirme, That ſince the</hi> King <hi>hath no hope of remedy from his Friends here at home, or abroad, his true</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt <hi>at preſent is by ſome meanes or other, to cloſe with that Partie in this</hi> Kingdome <hi>which they call</hi> Independent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Presbyter and his Party.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PResbiterie</hi> was no ſooner born at <hi>Geneva,</hi> but it was <hi>nurſt</hi> up here in <hi>England</hi> in the <hi>Wiſhes</hi> of many, as <hi>Heir apparent</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> For it's uſuall ever in all wordly <hi>Church-reformations</hi> (as well as thoſe of the <hi>State</hi>) to finde ſome men, either out of <hi>conſcience or envy,</hi> diſaffected to the ſettled Government: Out of <hi>Envy,</hi> when they miſſe of that <hi>Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which they expected by a <hi>change;</hi> out of <hi>conſcience,</hi> when they ſee a greater glory of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> beyond it, and therefore will not live by it, but beſide it, or above it; The truth whereof <hi>Experience</hi> hath told us in all the degrees of <hi>Reformation</hi> in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> from <hi>Popery</hi> to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie,</hi> from the <hi>Biſhop</hi> to the <hi>Presbyter:</hi> And I ſhall willingly allow the <hi>Presbyters</hi> (who reckon themſelves for the <hi>old Puritans</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) ſo much charity, as to think their <hi>diſaffection</hi> proceeded meerly from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>well-informed,</hi> becauſe I obſerve now an <hi>Impreſſa</hi> of divine glory and excellency in many of their <hi>Practiſes;</hi> But yet I would have them to know, that They are not yet come to Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> till they be able to prove the <hi>Chaire</hi> of a generall <hi>Aſſembly</hi> the very <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they ſhew all the lineaments of their Government derived <hi>naturally</hi> from <hi>Scripture,</hi> it will fright mens <hi>Conſciences</hi> and make Them diſclaim it for a monſter: For, the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> now contended for, is (as was the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108136:4"/>
Biſhops) but externall, <hi>prudentiall,</hi> matter of Form and Policy, and it is look't upon as ſo much the more <hi>intolerable,</hi> if rigidly preſt, by how much it opens a far <hi>wider</hi> gap for <hi>Tyranny;</hi> becauſe if the <hi>Biſhops</hi> made us grone under 24 <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> and but one <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us under almoſt 10000 <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> beſide the <hi>Torment</hi> of <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Provinciall Junto's Synods,</hi> and <hi>Aſſemblies?</hi> Were they able to prove one of them <hi>Scripturall,</hi> it were a little honeſter <hi>bandying</hi> againſt men of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent judgement, but ſince the continuation of that <hi>ridiculous Plea</hi> for a <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Divinum</hi> with <hi>compulſive</hi> power, can gain nothing but <hi>hatred</hi> from both the other <hi>parties,</hi> and muſt of neceſſity by <hi>diſobliging</hi> their <hi>friends</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of their enemies, and in time <hi>exaſperate</hi> both ſo far, that nothing will ſatisfie but an abolition of the <hi>new Form</hi> as <hi>immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</hi> and a reeſtabliſhing the <hi>old,</hi> upon more aſſurance of <hi>liberty:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the onely <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> is to allow the <hi>Independents</hi> their liberty of <hi>Church-way,</hi> to eſteem them as <hi>Brethren,</hi> and not to make dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in <hi>circumſtantials,</hi> a ground for <hi>perſecution.</hi> And this I ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther illuſtrate by reaſon. Firſt, it's as much <hi>madneſſe</hi> to perſecute men, becauſe they are not like us in <hi>opinion,</hi> as it were to quarrell with them when they reſemble us not, in outward complexion. For, ſince we loſt perfection in <hi>Adam,</hi> what ever <hi>knowledge</hi> we attain to now, is either <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> by the improving of naturall indowments; or elſe <hi>Divine,</hi> which is an influence from <hi>Heaven</hi> upon the <hi>Soul:</hi> For the former, we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden mediatly to the bounty of <hi>Nature</hi> and our own <hi>Induſtry;</hi> for the latter, immediatly to God. Therefore where we ſee any <hi>weaker</hi> in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then our <hi>ſelves,</hi> we ought to look upon them as <hi>deplorable,</hi> rather then <hi>damnable.</hi> Vain man! What made the difference betwixt thee and thy <hi>weak</hi> Brother? did not <hi>Free-grace?</hi> For, <hi>what haſt thou that thou didſt not receive? and God may reveal it to him alſo in due time.</hi> Secondly, the deſign of <hi>Conformity</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> hath been, and is the grand <hi>Cheat</hi> whereby the <hi>Devil</hi> makes men run a madding; and though it ever pretend a plauſible <hi>end</hi> of Cementing the <hi>State</hi> againſt <hi>Diviſion,</hi> yet pull off its <hi>Viſard,</hi> and you ſhall finde it to be both the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Nurſe</hi> of all <hi>Diviſion</hi> (as it ever was) throughout all <hi>Europe</hi> in matters of Religion: The witchcrafts of this <hi>Jezebel</hi> [it is] that trouble our <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> For, it is againſt common ſenſe and reaſon to expect, that ever men will be one in opinion (the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſaid, <hi>Quot Capita, tot Senſus,</hi>) ſo that thoſe which endeavour it ſeem to me, as if they meant to impriſon <hi>Aeolus</hi> and all his <hi>Sons [the 32 winds]</hi> in a Bag (as it is ſaid of the <hi>Lapland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi>) ſince <hi>Opinion</hi> blows from every point of the <hi>Compaſſe:</hi> And as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement of the <hi>Wind</hi> torments <hi>Nature</hi> with an Earth-quake, ſo to rob
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108136:5"/>
the <hi>Soul</hi> of its Freedom (which is far more agile and diffuſive) muſt needs cauſe a <hi>Colick</hi> (with inflammation) in the bowels of a Kingdom. And therefore till <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity-mongers</hi> be pointed at as the only Enemies of a <hi>State,</hi> and this wicked perſwaſion be wrought out of the hearts of men, that they ought to make all men walk that way <hi>par force</hi> which their <hi>Prieſts</hi> cry up for the right; till men be leſſe in the <hi>Letter</hi> that they may be <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> (which none but the <hi>Spirituall</hi> can apprehend) and untill they leave crying, <hi>Fire from Heaven</hi> againſt <hi>Brethren in the Faith,</hi> we ſhall alwayes have the Kingdom in a <hi>Flame,</hi> and (perhaps) <hi>themſelves</hi> may be the firſt in <hi>Aſhes.</hi> Thirdly, men under <hi>oppreſſion</hi> (though ſometime wiſe enough) become <hi>mad,</hi> and uſually trample down all <hi>Relations</hi> to make way for a <hi>deliverer,</hi> that gives hope of the leaſt remedy, and as the condition of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing</hi> alters, ſo all men do vary their <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and Principles. Fourthly, if a <hi>rigid</hi> courſe ſhould be proſecuted, and ſo a <hi>Breach</hi> be made betwixt thoſe who (for the major part) are <hi>one</hi> by <hi>Solemn Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Independent</hi> having that invincible Plea of <hi>Se defendendo</hi> on his ſide, the whole <hi>Scandall</hi> will retort upon the <hi>Presbyter:</hi> And if it be objected that the <hi>Independent</hi> occaſions the <hi>Breach,</hi> by oppoſing the Letter of the Covenant for an <hi>uniform</hi> Reformation, I anſwer, that the Covenant in its <hi>extent</hi> hath this <hi>ultimate</hi> Limitation, viz. <hi>according to the Word of God:</hi> No otherwiſe; The whole reſolves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that, as being all in all. And then, if both Parties be reduced to that <hi>Rule,</hi> let God and good men judge (for the World cannot) whoſe will be the <hi>Breach.</hi> Laſtly, a Moderate Condeſcention in the <hi>Presbyter</hi> will by keeping the other from extremes ſtop all new deſigns, and when there is more of the Spirit of Love in their proceedings, they will draw leſſe of Enmity. It will for ever confirm a Brotherly Union, which muſt prevent the forenamed Inſinuations of the Royall and Epiſcopall Party, and prove a Bulwark within, and a Wall of Braſſe about the Nation. From whence I once again infer, the ſole Intereſt of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyters is, to counter-work the <hi>King</hi> in his Intereſt, as their <hi>grand</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, by complying with the Independent, and it ought to be their wiſdom to look upon all men and Counſells in their own Party, [whether of the <hi>Purple</hi> or <hi>Sable</hi> robe] that Thunder in the behalf of a <hi>rigid</hi> Presbytery, as very Malignants, lurking among them under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a <hi>Reformation</hi> to draw in the leſſe wiſe and more worldly fiery <hi>Zelots,</hi> to Act for that Party under a diſguiſe which they pretend moſt to hate, and by Fulminating againſt our <hi>faſt friends,</hi> as <hi>Heretiques</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatiques,</hi> &amp;c. to ſhipwrack us in the Haven, and <hi>Caſſe</hi> all the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of this Parliament by <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:108136:5"/>
               <head>The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Independent Party.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS <hi>Presbytery</hi> is the <hi>Rivall</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> ſo <hi>Independency</hi> being of an higher <hi>Strain,</hi> than to admit of humane <hi>prudence</hi> in <hi>Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> her Principles ſtand indifferent towards either of them, as may ſerve moſt for her <hi>owne</hi> advantage. Both the other take in ſome of the <hi>wiſedome,</hi> and much of the <hi>power</hi> of the world, and ſo ſhare with the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of the world, to make up a <hi>Church,</hi> whereby they draw the <hi>world</hi> after them, becauſe the way is ſo ſutable to <hi>worldly reaſon;</hi> thus <hi>carnall</hi> men will ever be for a <hi>carnall</hi> Church: But <hi>Independents</hi> affirme the <hi>Church</hi> ought to be a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> building, framed of ſuch <hi>lively ſtones</hi> as are not of the <hi>world,</hi> nor of the wiſedome of the <hi>World,</hi> but founded only upon the wiſedome of <hi>God,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the word by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which they eſteeme ſufficient to conſtitute and maintain a <hi>Church,</hi> without any aſſiſtance from the Kingdomes of the <hi>world,</hi> whoſe power they leave <hi>entire</hi> unto themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Summ is this: both <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> by their Church-policy, ſtand <hi>Competitors</hi> with the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> leave all to him, ſave only the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which (if you will take his own word) is not of this <hi>world,</hi> and ſo can be no trouble to it, unleſs <hi>His</hi> be firſt troubled by it.</p>
               <p>By this deſcription then it appears, that the Government contended for by the other two is but <hi>meer</hi> Policie: and ſince their <hi>Politicks</hi> render them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly irreconcileable, <hi>Independencie</hi> (which owns no Policie) becomes the <hi>ballancing power</hi> betwixt them: And as it behoves either of the two, to ſtrive to weigh down the other, by a timely Cloſe with <hi>It,</hi> So the only <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Independency</hi> is to embrace that party where an <hi>union</hi> procures moſt <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> and little or no <hi>ſcandal;</hi> which I conceive may be expected rather from the <hi>Royall Epiſcopall</hi> party, then the other, upon theſe following <hi>Grounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Though principles of <hi>Faith</hi> ſhould ſway the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> to <hi>brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amity</hi> with the <hi>Independent,</hi> yet by their driving ſo furiouſly upon terms of diſcipline, and through their eagernes upon uniformity <hi>in the Letter,</hi> ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that glorious <hi>unity in the Spirit,</hi> (which is the very life of Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) they give little hope of favour, but rather expectation of a <hi>fiery Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> ſeeing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y begin to heat <hi>the Furnace</hi> already.</p>
               <p>Secondly, though <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſtand at a great diſtance; Yet ſetting aſide that groſſe mixture of <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) their diſcipline were far more tolerable, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they had power to exerciſe it to the utmoſt with compulſion, becauſe Tyranny cannot be ſo great in the hands of <hi>few,</hi> as <hi>many,</hi> So that if hereafter (in caſe <hi>Presbytery</hi> be ſetled) our former plagues be not a thouſand times trebled upon us, we muſt acknowledge our preſent freedom, only to the <hi>courteſie</hi> and goodnes of our <hi>Taskmaſters:</hi> But if <hi>corrupt times</hi> come on [as who can aſſure us they will not, ſince the old <hi>myſtery of iniquity</hi> is now in the world under a new <hi>Forme;</hi>] What then will become of our poſterity, when the yoake ſhall be faſtned to our necks by an <hi>Act of Parliament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, though the <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> are enemies to both <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> yet conſidering theſe have been extream civill in uſing their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108136:6"/>
and may now moſt oblige them in their <hi>loweſt</hi> condition: and it being poſſible that both their intereſts may ſtand together (with <hi>diſcretion</hi>) entire, then if Biſhops quit the exorbitant <hi>compulſive</hi> power, and the King give aſſurance againſt it <hi>for liberty of Conſcience,</hi> the enmity betwixt him and the <hi>Independent</hi> may be ſoon extinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, there can be no ſcandall to the <hi>Independent,</hi> by ſuch an <hi>union of intereſts,</hi> ſince the Woe-following ſcandall belongs to them alway, by whom the grounds of Scandall are neceſſitated. And therefore that the <hi>Scandall</hi> may clearely report upon <hi>Presbyter</hi> (as I proved before it muſt) the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> ought not to admit of a <hi>Breach</hi> till the <hi>Red Dragon</hi> begin to play <hi>Rex,</hi> till the <hi>Whore</hi> prepares to <hi>dye her Scarlet a new, and the pale Horſe of impriſonment and exile</hi> threaten a Range about the Streets.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s diſcovery of <hi>Intereſt</hi> may ſeem to portend ruine to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet it is far otherwiſe: For <hi>Independents</hi> ought not to looke upon it ſo, as to neglect them in whoſe <hi>priviledges</hi> and ſafety all <hi>Liberty</hi> is involved: But with all tenderneſſe to have regard unto them, as the onely <hi>Rampire</hi> againſt all kinds of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> ſince all proceedings thence againſt them as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> &amp;c. are actuated only by ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men, whoſe deſignes being laid <hi>in the darke,</hi> Time alone muſt diſcover: But that which will crowne <hi>Independent</hi> Intereſt [and which is indeed true <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Intereſt, though <hi>Presbyterians</hi> drive another way] is, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the King upon ſuch <hi>honourable</hi> Termes, that as he and they are in <hi>all reaſon</hi> obliged to down with the <hi>Dagon</hi> of a rigid <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ſo the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be managed with ſuch <hi>Caution,</hi> for the ſafety of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and aſſurance of <hi>Liberty</hi> in time to come, as may remove all <hi>Iealouſies</hi> and lay a ſure foundation for a <hi>laſting Peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis City bears the name of the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Royall Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the grand <hi>Emporium,</hi> the <hi>univerſall Exchange</hi> for Traffick; ſo that her ſole <hi>Intereſt</hi> is a free <hi>Trade,</hi> whereby having acquired large <hi>Demeſnes</hi> in all Parts, ſhe maintaines a conſiderable influence upon the whole, which makes her ſtand on <hi>tip-toe,</hi> looking down with diſdain upon all, as unable or unworthy to ſtand in competition with her <hi>ſingle Selfe.</hi> This conceit hath been much heightned by thoſe large <hi>Contributions</hi> thence, which have been the very <hi>Sinews</hi> of the <hi>War</hi> againſt the <hi>Royall Party;</hi> ſo that it's to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Huge <hi>Animal</hi> having found its own ſtrength, may prove <hi>Rampant,</hi> and contemne the <hi>Bridle,</hi> unleſſe a little corrected by <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore I thinke meet to lay down theſe enſuing <hi>conſiderations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that what they have hitherto done, muſt not be look't upon as done by their own ſtrength and Riches, but only as theſe received an Authority of <hi>Parliament</hi> to give life unto the Action, without which (as then, ſo) all deſignes [now, or hereafter] muſt prove <hi>abortive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, though the <hi>Citiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> pretend <hi>Religion</hi> to be the only neceſſary <hi>Appendix</hi> to that <hi>Trade,</hi> by claſping both together with a <hi>rigid Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:108136:6"/>
and ſuppoſe this the more pleaſing ſafe way, becauſe they are made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it is <hi>Divine,</hi> yet if they pleaſe to looke more narrowly upon the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> and the procedings of their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> they may learne the <hi>Scope</hi> of their <hi>State-Divinity</hi> is only to drive a <hi>Trade</hi> in the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> upon them and their <hi>Eſtates;</hi> which the <hi>City</hi> ſhal ſoone find, when the <hi>Presbyterian Charter</hi> is once confirmed <hi>by Act of Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, if onely <hi>even rekonings make long friends,</hi> then it's like this hot love to a <hi>Presbyterie</hi> may end in a <hi>Divorce</hi> before the three yeares end, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the <hi>Accompts</hi> ſhall be caſt up betwixt <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity,</hi> that worm-eaten Reverend <hi>Cheat</hi> of <hi>diſtinction</hi> betwixt Brethren. It's true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſome of them ſhall be admitted to a partnerſhip in the <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and this is the very <hi>De-coy</hi> to allure them on, but uſually the <hi>preaching</hi> Presbyter ſwayes All, and he is a very ſilly one indeed that knowes not how to do it, ſince they either ſtand or fall according to his Report of their good <hi>Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> in the opinion of the generall <hi>Aſſembly</hi> [that <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies,</hi> where the <hi>Lay-Vulgars</hi> muſt not enter;] which <hi>neat</hi> contrivance of inviſible <hi>Clock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke,</hi> will be ſure to have a <hi>wheele</hi> going in all affaires of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Fourthly, Suppoſe that the <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> themſelves ſhould have fair Play from the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> yet what comfort will that be to the reſt of the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> who muſt be in little better condition then <hi>gally-ſlaves,</hi> when the <hi>Elderſhip</hi> ſhall have an <hi>Oare</hi> in every <hi>Boat?</hi> And this appeares by the power given them to ſuſpend perſons from, and admit to the <hi>Supper,</hi> as they ſhall ſee cauſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to an <hi>Ordinance</hi> in that behalfe: in which <hi>Ordinance,</hi> there being no leſs than 80. ſins enumerated (and an addition of many more endeavoured) any one of which upon <hi>Conviction,</hi> may include a man guilty, if they pleaſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him: then it is cleare alſo, that ſince a man can hardly do any thing that comes not within the compaſs of thoſe <hi>Sins,</hi> all men muſt be irrefragably ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to their pleaſure in all their dealings, or elſe be delivered up to the <hi>Devill</hi> [forſooth] by <hi>Excommunication.</hi> Where then will <hi>freedome</hi> be in a <hi>corrupt</hi> Presbytery when the Citizens ſhall not dare to diſpoſe of their own <hi>Eſtates,</hi> nor weare <hi>Clothes</hi> as they pleaſe, nor manage their <hi>Trades</hi> to fructifie <hi>percent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> nor uſe an hundred other <hi>fine feats,</hi> without a friend or <hi>feeling</hi> in the <hi>Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> What will become of our <hi>Lawyers</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo, when it is an caſie matter to make the ſame <hi>Ordinance,</hi> a <hi>Shoing-horne</hi> to draw on all <hi>caſes,</hi> depending betwixt man and man, into their owne <hi>Conſiſtori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, they may do well to conſider, that if they ſhal drive any other <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> than <hi>Trade,</hi> as their owne peculiar, which may intr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nch upon the <hi>union of intereſts</hi> before mentioned, or hinder them from uniting by under-prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the other <hi>Party,</hi> it's cleare then, that their power and greatneſs will be <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> and become odious to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> For, their <hi>High Termes</hi> already with the Parliament, and the eſtabliſhing of a <hi>Militia</hi> in their owne hands, <hi>distinct</hi> from the reſt of the Kingdome, makes <hi>wiſe men</hi> whiſper, as if they meant to found a new <hi>Religious Democracie,</hi> by reſolving the <hi>Co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108136:7"/>
of power in the Lord <hi>Major, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Common Councell</hi> into a <hi>popular Senate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, I would have them conſider that the <hi>Jealouſies</hi> of <hi>States and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are great, and cannot brook any <hi>Rivall,</hi> nor will they judge themſelves ſafe, as long as any one <hi>Corporation</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> make a ſhew of <hi>Competition</hi> in wealth and <hi>power.</hi> Nor can it be ſafe for <hi>Subjects</hi> to diſcover them too far in this way, leſt they teach <hi>Princes</hi> to ſecure and inrich themſelves by ſeizing upon <note n="*" place="margin">Facile eſt Baculum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire, ut caedas Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> 
                  <hi>Theirs.</hi> What made the <hi>Abbies</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> ſo lookt on, but only their great <hi>Wealth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what was the main <hi>Plea</hi> to ruine them (as <hi>Princes</hi> (if poſſible) will have ſome coulour of <hi>Law to</hi> ſet off actions of this nature) but their holding vaſt poſſeſſions in their hands which could not paſſe from man to man ſo lay <hi>dead</hi> to the prejudice of the <hi>Common-Wealth?</hi> I wiſh the <hi>City</hi> to ponder, whether there be not the ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> farr more preſſing, againſt the unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable <hi>Revenues</hi> of their <hi>Halls</hi> and ſeverall <hi>Companies,</hi> thoſe inſatiable <hi>Gulphs</hi> which <hi>ſwallow</hi> up ſo great a part of the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> And whether their high <hi>Raunting</hi> may not bring on the ſame <hi>Fate</hi> hereafter, on the ſame ground, upon the firſt <hi>tempting</hi> opportunity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſince their <hi>Presbytery</hi> is onely of the <hi>World,</hi> they may doe well to conſider how it is like to thrive in the World, ſince ſo few even amongſt <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> are willing to entertaine it, and the <hi>Counties</hi> abroad are ſome of them ſo wiſe, others ſo <hi>croſſ-grain'd</hi> to all <hi>Novelty:</hi> that they generally <hi>deteſt</hi> it: And therfore if it ſhall appeare that the <hi>Citizens</hi> are the men, which reſolve to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt both <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Independent</hi> [whoſe <hi>Intereſts</hi> tend to a ſpeedy hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Peace</hi> &amp; juſt Liberty] for the ſetling of that <hi>government</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> which neither we, nor our <hi>Children</hi> ſhal be able to beare, it's moſt certaine, that the <hi>Odium</hi> of a SECOND VVARR will reflect upon them, and the whole burden of <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>expence</hi> reſt upon their <hi>ſhoulders:</hi> And then they may gueſſe what the conſequence will bee, when their <hi>Purſes</hi> are exhauſted and both the other <hi>Parties</hi> [carying the <hi>Kingdome</hi> before them] ſhall be forced into an unanimous <hi>deſigne of revenge,</hi> to ſcourge their <hi>pride,</hi> with ſuch an <hi>alteration</hi> [if not <hi>utter deſtruction</hi>] as may verifie [perhaps] the <hi>Fagg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> of the old Propheſie, that YORK SHAL BE.</p>
               <p>From all which I may ſumm up this <hi>Concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the true <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> is to coole by degrees toward a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie</hi> (not all at once, leſt it be accounted <hi>Levity,</hi>) And in the mean time to ſtand <hi>neutrall</hi> ſo farr as not to make a <hi>diſtinct party,</hi> nor drive any <hi>deſigne</hi> at <hi>Home</hi> or at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by <hi>hoiſting</hi> up <hi>ſupernumerary Votes,</hi> &amp; pulling down all others with <hi>Remonſtrative</hi> or <hi>Petitionary Out-cries,</hi> but to leave the <hi>Presbyterian cauſe</hi> to ſtand or fall, by <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>ſober debate</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that being the leſs look't upon in ſo <hi>turbulent</hi> a time, They may enjoy their <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> without <hi>Envy</hi> and the ſhaken Kingdom [they kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſtill] may have time to ſettle, and recover the priſtine health and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of a glorious Monarchy.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:108136:7"/>
               <l>O Cives, Cives, <hi>quae vos Dementia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tanti non eſt</hi> Civilia <hi>bella moveri.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which had been long endeavoured in <hi>vaine</hi> by ſeverall <hi>Kings,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at length (through the prudence of <hi>Henry</hi> 7. effected, I meane the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of both <hi>Crownes</hi> in the perſon of one <hi>Prince;</hi> King <hi>Iames</hi> willing (as much as might bee) to <hi>burie</hi> the remembrance of <hi>diſ-union</hi> and <hi>allay</hi> the <hi>deadly feuds</hi> running <hi>in a bloud</hi> betwixt the <hi>borderers,</hi> thought meet to <hi>curtaile</hi> his <hi>title</hi> of the uſuall <hi>diſtinct</hi> names of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and as <hi>both</hi> made but one <hi>Iſland,</hi> ſo he compriſed both in that one ancient <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellative</hi> of <hi>great Britain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> under a <hi>native</hi> King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was an <hi>happy</hi> occaſion for that <hi>poore</hi> Kingdom, to augment their <hi>repute</hi> and <hi>fortunes;</hi> and as in ſuch <hi>caſes</hi> it is uſuall for the <hi>leſſe,</hi> to drive a purchaſe upon the <hi>greater,</hi> by <hi>cloſing in</hi> as neare as <hi>jealouſie</hi> will permit; ſo the <hi>Scots</hi> (inamoured of the <hi>cluſters</hi> of our <hi>Canaan</hi>) loſt no time in getting ground on this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> viz. <hi>Tweed,</hi> till many of them became poſſeſſors of <hi>fair vineyards,</hi> and were able to <hi>vie</hi> Lordſhips with our wealthieſt <hi>Engliſh.</hi> To this height they <hi>arrived</hi> through the favour of that <hi>King,</hi> which drew many more into a deſire of the <hi>warmer Sun,</hi> and an <hi>emulation</hi> of their <hi>friends</hi> happineſſe here in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But toward the <hi>latter</hi> end of King <hi>James,</hi> the <hi>paſſages</hi> began to be <hi>blockt up at</hi> Court by the <hi>Prelates</hi> faction: who judged it dangerous for their <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie,</hi> to ſee men of that <hi>Nation</hi> in too great a number &amp; power, near hand, for fear leſt the ſame <hi>humor</hi> which had depreſſed <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> pomp there, might in time have an <hi>influence</hi> here alſo; ſo that by this means not only the affections of King <hi>Iames,</hi> (whoſe ordinary <hi>Apophthegme</hi> was, no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>King</hi>) were a little <hi>weaned;</hi> but he being dead, the ſame <hi>Counſells</hi> prevailed upon the new <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>Son</hi> (one eaſily wrought any way to gratifie his <hi>Clergy) to a diſ-obliging</hi> of the <hi>Scots:</hi> who ſeeing themſelves now quite out of hope of <hi>thriving</hi> by the <hi>Kings</hi> favour; and knowing well upon what <hi>ground,</hi> and by whoſe <hi>meanes</hi> things were thus carried, concluded then there was no way to get into the <hi>Nation,</hi> but upon the <hi>ruine</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops;</hi> which muſt neceſſarily follow, if they could introduce the <hi>Presbiteriall</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which <hi>themſelves</hi> had received in <hi>Scotland:</hi> and this they found was no hard matter to <hi>effect,</hi> ſince there were <hi>many</hi> that way <hi>affected</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and their <hi>affections</hi> highly <hi>inflamed,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>rigorous</hi> dealing and <hi>tyrannicall</hi> pride of ſome <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> which rendred their whole <hi>Order</hi> and government, odious to the more <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> &amp; prepared the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (<hi>hood-winkt</hi>) to entertain any <hi>change,</hi> though to their own <hi>prejudice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being (on the <hi>other</hi> ſide) immediately reſented by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> they judged it beſt to be <hi>before-hand</hi> with the <hi>Scots;</hi> and firſt (to try their <hi>patience,</hi> and Pick a <hi>quarrel,</hi> on purpoſe to <hi>tame</hi> them by <hi>force</hi>) a <hi>new Liturgie</hi> was contrived, ſent, and <hi>impoſed</hi> upon them; the <hi>offer</hi> whereof bred ſo much
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108136:8"/>
indignation in the one <hi>party,</hi> as a <hi>refuſall</hi> did in the other (both glad enough of the <hi>occaſion,</hi>) that a <hi>war</hi> immediately enſued; wherein though the <hi>King</hi> were ingaged on the <hi>Biſhops</hi> part, yet the <hi>Scots</hi> got moſt of <hi>Honour</hi> and (the <hi>war</hi> being ended) much <hi>money</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi> among their <hi>friends</hi> in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> which ſo <hi>indeared</hi> them, that a new <hi>rupture</hi> falling out betwixt <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> they had an eaſie <hi>in-let</hi> to build themſelves (with high <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi>) a more ſure <hi>intereſt</hi> than ever, in this <hi>Nation;</hi> which was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht by the mutuall ingagement of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of each <hi>Kingdom</hi> to other (as <hi>brethren</hi>) in the firm <hi>bond</hi> of a <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which <hi>lant-skip</hi> of diſcourſe it appeares, as the <hi>Scots</hi> have now attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>pitch</hi> of their <hi>deſires,</hi> by a <hi>faſt foot</hi> in the <hi>fat ſoyle of England,</hi> through <hi>mutuall Covenanting,</hi> (which hath been long a <hi>contriving</hi> and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſtruggled for,) ſo they ought to proſecute the <hi>Covenant</hi> (the <hi>vitals</hi> of their <hi>hope</hi>) with all due reſpect, <hi>tenderneſſe,</hi> and <hi>caution</hi> (according to the <hi>rationall</hi> drift of it) toward the people of <hi>England,</hi> leſt their <hi>proceedings</hi> become odious, and <hi>themſelves</hi> be <hi>kick'd off</hi> again with diſdain and <hi>enmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall preſent them with a few <hi>conſiderations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, let them be pleaſed to remember, that the people look upon them but as <hi>inferiours,</hi> and therefore muſt needs <hi>ſwell</hi> high with <hi>indignation,</hi> if they buſie themſelves over-much in the affaires of <hi>England,</hi> knowing in how high ſcorne it was taken, that they ſhould claime an <hi>intereſt</hi> (as once they had the boldneſſe to doe, in their <hi>Papers</hi> given into the <hi>Parliament</hi>) in <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals</hi> of matters <hi>meerly</hi> relating to our <hi>welfare:</hi> And ſince all men know, that though they were admitted to ingage here (<hi>neceſſity</hi> ſo requiring it) as <hi>equals</hi> and <hi>competitors</hi> in the ſame <hi>cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> being <hi>ſuppoſed equally</hi> involved in the ſame <hi>common</hi> danger; yet were they indeed but <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenaries,</hi> in <hi>pay</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, who might have had <hi>Germans</hi> or <hi>Swiſſers</hi> at the ſame <hi>rate,</hi> &amp; (perhaps) no more <hi>prejudice</hi> to the <hi>Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I muſt confeſſe, it behoves the <hi>Scot predicant</hi> (if poſſible) to ſee <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> caſhiered root and branch, and their owne <hi>form ſtated</hi> here, in a ſure ſucceſſion: that ſo a <hi>correſpondence</hi> being cheriſhed between Clergy of the ſame <hi>garb</hi> and <hi>humour,</hi> in both <hi>Countries,</hi> they may freely <hi>toſſe thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bolts of excommunication,</hi> on both ſides, to gratifie each other, and ſo be able to terrifie all <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> that dare be <hi>averſe</hi> in either <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and <hi>promote</hi> ſuch onely to <hi>places of truſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>poorer</hi> ſpirits will vaſſallize their <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Genius</hi> to ſerve their ends. And I confeſſe, it behoves ſuch <hi>great ones,</hi> as have already <hi>link'd</hi> themſelves in <hi>deſign</hi> with the <hi>Clergie,</hi> to ſtick cloſe to them a while, for their owne <hi>credit</hi> and <hi>ſecurity,</hi> except they can handſomly retreat with <hi>ſpeed;</hi> yet both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Gentry of this <hi>gang,</hi> may conſider that ſuch a <hi>courſe</hi> cannot ſtand long in <hi>England;</hi> where being <hi>Myriads</hi> of more <hi>generous</hi> ſoules than in <hi>Scotland,</hi> they muſt alwaies expect a <hi>flying out</hi> into any extrems, that yeeld the leaſt hope of an advantage to <hi>throw their riders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108136:8"/>Thirdly, if the <hi>Scots</hi> plead <hi>conſcience</hi> for <hi>extirping</hi> the Government by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as bound thereto by <hi>Covenant;</hi> yet ſeeing <hi>Biſhop</hi> is every <hi>jot</hi> as <hi>wholſome</hi> a word, and as much <hi>Scripturall</hi> as <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and that our weaker <hi>Brethren</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are <hi>wedded</hi> to that Forme, as more tolerable than any other, and more <hi>ſutable</hi> to the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Monarchie;</hi> I ſuppoſe, that the admiſſion of a <hi>Biſhop mortified, regulated,</hi> and <hi>pruned</hi> of his <hi>ſuperfluities,</hi> will no whit claſh with the ſenſe of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> For it is plaine, that the <hi>ſcope</hi> of it is not againſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the <hi>Abſtract,</hi> but in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete,</hi> as laden with an <hi>accumulation</hi> of <hi>Deanes, Deanes</hi> and <hi>Chapters, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, Chancellours, Commiſſaries,</hi> &amp;c. though if theſe alſo were <hi>admitted</hi> again, as I cannot ſee how they may be well <hi>refuſed,</hi> yet the <hi>Scots</hi> (for their part) and thoſe of their <hi>party</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> having endeavoured their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to <hi>extirp</hi> it, they have done all that the <hi>Covenant</hi> requires, though it be not effected. But ſeeing moſt in <hi>England</hi> will not be content without it, and nothing but another <hi>Conqueſt</hi> can <hi>force</hi> any other upon them, me think <hi>rationall</hi> men ſhould ſit down content with a diſcharge of their conſciences, in having ſeriouſly <hi>endeavoured</hi> the <hi>extirping</hi> it to their power (further then which the <hi>Covenant</hi> doth not binde them,) rather then aime at an <hi>impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> in <hi>reaſon,</hi> or venture a <hi>ſad ſcore</hi> upon <hi>conſcience,</hi> in imbroyling two <hi>Kingdomes</hi> again, to an inevitable ruine of a <hi>third;</hi> which can never be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from <hi>Scripture,</hi> in the behalf of <hi>Principles of Faith,</hi> which are the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> much leſſe upon point of <hi>Diſciplin,</hi> which is but the <hi>ſhadow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, if a <hi>deſigne</hi> be followed, to force their Government upon this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſo generally deteſted by <hi>reaſonable</hi> men, the <hi>war</hi> cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bee <hi>long-liv'd</hi> here, where the <hi>thing</hi> contended for is ſo ill <hi>befriended,</hi> but muſt of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> be tranſlated toward <hi>Scotland,</hi> where it had its <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall:</hi> And though the <hi>Scots</hi> need not feare, being valiant enough, and having one <hi>advantage</hi> above all other men, in poſſeſſing <hi>little</hi> that may <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite</hi> men to a conqueſt; yet it will be <hi>chaſtiſement</hi> enough to be beaten home, &amp; kept there from their uſuall way of thriving, by <hi>intercourſe with England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, ſince that their <hi>Presbyterie</hi> is more of the <hi>World,</hi> and ſo like to be more <hi>troubleſome</hi> to it than <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> it will bee an <hi>occaſion</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to <hi>prye</hi> into the <hi>grounds</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> ſo earneſt <hi>preſſing</hi> that <hi>government</hi> upon them: and finding by the <hi>Proeme</hi> of this particular <hi>draught</hi> (which <hi>wiſe obſerving</hi> men cannot be ignorant of) that <hi>wordly</hi> reſpects firſt made them bring it in hither, the greater part of men here (which are <hi>worldly</hi>) will endeavour to preſerve themſelves againſt all ſuch <hi>worldly incroachments</hi> under <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>Religion:</hi> and though it be preſented in a new <hi>dreſſe,</hi> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Reformation;</hi> yet ſince it muſt prove no other, than an <hi>Aſſaſſination</hi> of the <hi>Monarchie,</hi> and a <hi>Reducing</hi> of the old <hi>Privado's</hi> which <hi>oppreſſed</hi> us at <hi>Court</hi> to <hi>overwh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lm</hi> us with <hi>new</hi> ones quite throughout the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> it is like that the love of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ingly</hi> Government (ſo ſurely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>jealouſie</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> will render men <hi>implacable</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:108136:9"/>
to all; that keep a hand in a <hi>rigid Presbyterie, &amp; urge</hi> them to apply <hi>deſperate</hi> remedies to be <hi>cured</hi> of it, as the grand <hi>canker-worm</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, to <hi>deſigne</hi> that upon a people which their <hi>conſtitutions</hi> will not beare, ordinary <hi>Braines</hi> muſt conceive can have no <hi>ground</hi> in <hi>policie,</hi> unleſſe there be ſome certainty which way to <hi>maſter</hi> them: and therfore the <hi>Scots</hi> and their <hi>favorites</hi> may do well to conſider, how they can go <hi>through ſtitch</hi> with the buſines againſt a generous people, impatient of the <hi>yoake.</hi> It is not in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where men are <hi>poore,</hi> and ſo the more eaſily <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved,</hi> and led about to ſerve the <hi>ends</hi> of the <hi>Grandees</hi> amongſt them; but being <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their <hi>freedomes,</hi> will entertain no more here from the <hi>perſwaſions</hi> of men, than what they can make <hi>viſible</hi> by <hi>reaſon,</hi> as condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the <hi>generall good;</hi> ſo that the <hi>ground-work</hi> of all actions muſt be laid, according to the peoples <hi>inclination,</hi> and not the <hi>faction</hi> of particular men, be they never ſo potent in <hi>wealth,</hi> or <hi>wiſedome.</hi> By this <hi>rule</hi> they may judge, what their <hi>friends</hi> are able to doe for the <hi>Presbyterian cauſe</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſince moſt men <hi>un-interreſted</hi> that way are of a contrary mind, I wiſh them to <hi>conſider,</hi> that if by <hi>ſtriving againſt the ſtreame,</hi> they loſe their <hi>hold</hi> now, it can never be recovered again upon the ſame pretence, and (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) many ages will hardly afford the like; and therefore if the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhall proceed to <hi>ſcrue</hi> themſelves in by their <hi>engineers</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (more <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> already then the former) to the oppreſſion of <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Loquor ad ſenſum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi.</note> 
                  <hi>Independent conſciences,</hi> and indeavour to found <hi>them</hi> with an <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> power, upon the <hi>blood</hi> of both <hi>Countries,</hi> by a <hi>new war,</hi> the <hi>ancient Antipathy</hi> muſt needs <hi>revive,</hi> and bee reared againe (like <hi>Adrian's</hi> wall) as a perpetuall <hi>Barr</hi> betwixt the <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence I may conclude, the <hi>caſe</hi> thus ſtanding; that the only <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> is, to preſerve themſelves in the <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by a <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>faire conſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> in behalfe of a <hi>Presbytery;</hi> which being by <hi>Covenant</hi> to be judged according to the <hi>word of God,</hi> they have the leſſe reaſon to ſtand for their own <hi>way</hi> here, becauſe they take <hi>little</hi> beſides the bare <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Preſbytery</hi> out of the <hi>word,</hi> and ſo having no pretence to found a <hi>quarrell,</hi> but only upon ſome parcels of the <hi>letter</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> I ſee no reaſon they have to be angry, if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> give them leave to inioy <hi>their</hi> owne in peace at home, and in the meane time take leave to ſettle things here, for the good of this <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Church Government,</hi> as they judge anſwerable to their <hi>principles,</hi> (according to the <hi>Word</hi>) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they apprehend the <hi>Covenant</hi> was firſt <hi>intended, framed</hi> and <hi>founded.</hi> And ſo the heat of <hi>controverſie</hi> being laid by, a <hi>brotherly condeſcenſion</hi> on both ſides, in matter of <hi>religious</hi> concernment, the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>union,</hi> in all <hi>civill</hi> reſpects, may be eſtabliſhed, and kept <hi>inviolable</hi> betwixt the <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Dirno, &amp; aedifico, muto quadrata rotundis.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108136:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
